so this is uh maim nikaya 21 just an
excert says because even if Bandits were
to sever you savagely limb by limb with
a two handled saw he who gave rise to a
mind of hate towards them would not be
carrying out my
teaching so Vante uh you frequently
emphasize or the suitors frequently
emphasize that an Arun remains
unaffected even in the most challenging
circumstances so I have three
questions one can you clarify how their
perspective differs from that of an
ordinary
person what causes them to remain free
from anger in the face of Cruelty and
three what
misconception in that way of thinking or
or what kind of wrong view leads to Ill
will mhm that's kind of one question but
uh yeah well really it boils down to the
to the same thing that differentiates
from which is the uh
uh
inability um of his
mind to Crave against suffering when
it's felt the Mind becomes
felt the Mind becomes
unable to resist it so it's not
something it's not something you
do it's not a matter of choice it's not
like suffering affects putuj then he
chooses to stop resisting it and then he
becomes a
sod so it's more like a putuj recognizes
that the root of suffering is the Mind
resisting the unpleasant feeling when it
touches it and that causes another layer
of suffering in and of itself which is
really what duka is it's that that
second arrow that the Su SP about so
then through gradual
training AJ can then uh train his own
mind and basically teach it uh train it
to
unlearn how to turn against itself how
to how to just jump into resistance
against an unpleasant
feeling and with that training is sort
of uh developed to fruition when the
suffering touches that buj he just sees
that his mind is not going against it
internally like he might do things about
it externally but internally that
Eternal internal dimension of mind um
sort of turning over itself so to speak
when pain touches it and not wanting
that that that has disappeared because
he trained mind pretty much and at that
point he's not pan anymore
so now you take the same principle all
the way so then you recognize further
layers of training that mind like now
when the arrow of suffering strikes you
the Mind does not crave against it does
not like has that instantaneous attitude
of I must get rid of this this very
moment that's gone and because of that
he has sort of experienced freedom from
that second
Arrow but within that there might be
other sort of subtler things now that
the Mind still leans towards leans away
or wants to ignore so then he just
starts to train the mind further pushes
it further and refines that training
even further so what differentiates
arand then from soana sakami anagami and
certainly Froman is that mind is
completely depleted any ability to turn
against itself when anything unpleasant
happens to it it just cannot go that way
and the reason why I cannot go that way
is because it was always impossible to
go that way but not fully understanding
that that's why you were going that
way and and that's why it's irreversible
training the mind in that way it's
irreversible you can't then if the mind
has fully
uprooted that craving tan against
whatever's felt there is no going back from that it
felt there is no going back from that it
cannot craving cannot be
reintroduced so that's why arahant is
incapable to have ill will even in the
most extreme
circumstances not because his
perspective of what's happening to him
is just always sharp always fully
maintained he might be completely
bewildered by physical pain externally
he might not be able to like his senses
might not be able to compute
correctly but
internally regardless of his six senses
falling apart the chitt his mind mind cannot
apart the chitt his mind mind cannot
possibly turn against any aspect or the
whole experience at all cannot turn
against it and again not like um well
you can say aran's mind for the sake of
expression but it's not like that
arahant is telling his mind not to do it
no that mind has been trained beforehand
and now that mind has become unable to
do that it has become unable to turn
against itself to turn against pain to
LEAP towards pleasure to turn towards
ignor of the neutral
feeling how well by fully understanding
the nature of what it has been turning
towards or against
beforehand in other words it's
like you will become well you won't have
to tell yourself to drop a burning lump
of
coal if you learn that oh that's why my
hand has always been burning that's why
because he was always painful if you
recognize that now you wouldn't even
have to think about it it's enough just
to feel the heat and you will go away
from it mentally certainly so the point
is it's not aran's choice to not have
ill will it's just that his mind is
completely um not
capable of uh having any degree of
Leaning away from any displeasure that
might be inflicted upon it equally
aran's mind is not capable of leaning
toward words welcoming any pleasure they
might be inflicted upon it and Aran
knows that so that's why like he knows that he
that so that's why like he knows that he
knows he has trained the Mind through
right understanding and gradual training
and then things happen this so that
happens and he just realizes that his
mind that mind that he's been training
and keeping an eye on and containing is
not acting the same way as it did before
it's just it's not leaping AT Pleasure
it's actually remains unmoved in the
prospect of Temptations equally it's not
shivering away from Pain it remains
unmoved it's not afraid of it because he
knows that where truly pain comes from
which is that
internal mind turning against itself as
I often say that internal
craving that that's been depleted so
those mental
attitudes uh is something that arahan
has completely trained his mind out
of and and now whatever were to happen
to him well he doesn't know which way
things will go which way the
circumstances will go but he knows that
one thing is for sure mind will not
crave against it internally it will not
try to eat itself just to avoid a
pain and that gives all the confidence
you need for complete
Liberation and that's something sopan
understands as well he just has not
fully develop that principle in a sense
um it does not perme at any every
circumstance in every direction in every
possible permutations there would be
things that would still make him a bit
kind of um caught up and so on but
fundamentally on that most base
level soana cannot be
struck by that second Arrow of mental
anguish and
turmoil and anybody can relate to it
like I'm sure everybody in their life
has experienced something that the mind
just keeps revolving around something of
the unpleasant kind they would keep you
awake at night they would make you
worried and um and they would kind of
it's enough for little things to just
remind you of it and you just couldn't
you well you can't help it and you just
find your mind already
fully reaching towards it trying to
cancel it trying to resolve it trying to
deny it and then you just have to go
through the until the Mind tires out and
you get distracted with something and
and then you just pray that nothing
reminds the mind of that which already
bothers it and when it does again and
again and
again it's kind of pretty much the
nature of dukka whether it's stress or
anxiety or traumas or whatever that's
pretty much the common thread the mind
just going back at it and uh you
suffering on account of
it but if you could you would stop that
mind you would tell it stop and if that
mind were to listen to you it would stop
but it doesn't because you can't it
doesn't understand your language
basically so you can tell it what all
all you want you can talk to it all all
you want but it won't hear you however
you can train it you can train it with
with basically the the the the steps
that the Buddha laid out you can contain
it you can train it you can harness it
you can direct it you can learn how to
read it signs and tokens and
indications so again the simile of the
cows roaming around everyone's pastures
eating unwarily and being punished and
you being punished on account of it
that's pretty much it mine just won't
let go just revolves just spins just
spins who said what and another what
happened and then you suffer you can't
sleep at night full of anxiety full of
restlessness full of worry everything is
a trigger
now oh but if it only if only I could
stop thinking it's like well again
thinking is the mind's domain thinking
is what the Mind does so you can't stop
that that's not your doing so to
speak you sure you can distract yourself
you can look away from it but
fundamentally that mind for as long as
untrained it will always carry the
ability to turn against you to turn
against itself to turn against anything
that's felt if he deems unwanted and
that will cause you suffering that will
because you fear pain anxiety stress
everything that
follows so you train it pretty much
through the gradual training first
virtue that that contains the behavior
regardless of of of what your views are
and and where the emphasis is then sense
restraint again it might seem like an
indirect thing to you oh well virtue and
sense restraint does not bear direct
relevance to my problem to my trauma to
my stress to my suffering
well no it Bears it doesn't bear direct
um connection to the specifics of your
trauma of your memories of your
experience of your past but it Bears a
very direct connection to the wild
wildness wilderness of your own mind
which is the fundamental reason for your
suffering it's not because of what
happened to you it's because the mind by
being an untrained
entity uh encountered something that
made it very kind of um
agitated angry um made it turn against you
angry um made it turn against you
against everything maybe want to deny
all of it and that's the utmost pain
fundamentally so that's why like the the
the simile from that Su illustrates the
point that even if the highway robbers
are chopping your limbs circumstances
are not the cause of suffering are not
the cause of ill will by same uh proxy
they are not circum Es are not caused of
central desire either so recognizing
then that keeping the precepts and
guarding of the sense doors and
watchfulness of your intentions so like
what do you want to do why you want to
do it all those Reflections we often
talk about yes absolutely there's no
relevance no direct connection to what
happened to you when you were 5 years
old or the stress you're experiencing
because of your work or this but it's
the direct line the direct fuel for your
mind for its Wilderness or for its
tameness if you contain
it so the simil as we saw often repeat
it of wild elephant you need to tame it
you need to train it you need to make it
obey you well you can try and talk to it
and you know take get get some
counseling and psychotherapy but again
it does not speak that
language what you need to do is first
catch it so stop allowing it to spill itself
it so stop allowing it to spill itself
out into physical actions into verbal
actions contain it and then it will kick
and scream and urinate and defecate and
rebel but now it's it's it's it's tied
down with the leather
straps and when it comes down when there
is when it realizes there is no
compromise I am not being let off the
hook now then you well first of all you would
now then you well first of all you would
see that you would see now that the mind
is not as rebellious against precepts
although he's been trying to find the
ways to make you break it to make you go
against them because yeah look look he
has nothing to do with with this or that
or with this anxiety or with that
anxiety yeah but it has to do with you
and you are the reason that the
circumstances cause me anxieties and so
on the mind is the
reason so you have to stop listening to
these wild inclinations of your own mind
because that's why the Mind remains
pretty much in charge of you not other
way around so once it's contained once
once it's tamed in that sense you then
see like oh look I got this mind trapped
now there is a
circumstance that it's
unpleasant and uh and I saw the mind's
reaction to
it and I saw that ah that was why I used
to suffer because before that mind that
now I trapped through through Perpetual
virtue establishment of virtue aggregate
of virtue sense restraint and pretty
much 24/7 watchfulness of my intentions
and containing it basically I see it now
as an entity there that reacts to this
and that as opposed to before where I
didn't see any of that where it was
completely identified with me with my
point of view so when something would
when circumstances would arise and mine
would kick and scream against I was just
thinking it's me who is kicking and
screaming against it so there was like
no no no buffers on nothing that I could
see in between it was just this and then
the complete overwhelming anxiety and
fear but now when the mind is trapped
and contained I actually circumstance arise
contained I actually circumstance arise
and I see the mind doing that not me I'm
not doing
it the mind is trying to go against it
and then equally well once you start to
see that then even the mind kind of
recognizes okay so I can't fool you
anymore before when I did when I did
like sort of leap towards pleasure or I
I resisted the pain or I ignored the
neutral feeling you thought it was you
and it was great cuz I was invisible
basically so you completely thought it's
you and oh then I need to do this or
need to do that completely missing where
the problem was and the problem was
simply mind doing it to you cuz you
haven't trained it now you can hate your
mind or something but you wouldn't hate
a wild elephant because well that's all
it knows its Wilderness is all it knows
so it would be kind of stupid to to to
sort of feel ill will towards that in
the same sense like you can't blame your
mind for doing that because that's what
an untrained mind can only
do so all of this understanding begins
with saati seeing the signs of your mind I
saati seeing the signs of your mind I
seeing your mind as an actual entity as
an actual phenomenon
there through trapping it rightly taming
it containing it Discerning the
intentions fully develop that training
so there are so that there are no
circumstances left however extreme that
can still make you forget where the
problem is and when you can't forget
where the problem is that mind will be
completely then tamed and there will be
no Kicking and Screaming regardless of
what comes that way and there will be no
there will be basically uh incapability
of
suffering in your
experience so so say you contain the
mind that elephant in that boundary of
precepts and so on and then something
you know uh that used to make it upset
or lustful or angry comes in its view so
that elephant starts getting or roused
up so what do you do exactly so it's
like okay so I'm keeping the precepts
now surely I must be containing the mind
there is something that's upsetting me
what do I do well that's the point you
realize that whatever you're supposed to
do is you're already doing
it trap your mind don't let that wild
animal go get loose that's what you need
to do so something upsetting something
challenging comes how do I deal with
this I deal with this by not dealing
with it but by dealing with this mind
remaining trapped that's what I need to
remain sort of vigilant of so you're
kind of keeping it safe in a way Lu well
you're keeping it safe for your own sake
he doesn't know what's and for its own
sake but the mind doesn't know what it's
good for itself it's a wild
animal but even more you are the one
getting P punished for its actions
that's the whole simil of the cow her
and and and a Shepherd that the Buddha
gave you realize oh yeah it's like this
mind does this and I'm the one who
suffers so then that and that's again
like people think sense restraint is
just to avoid looking looking avoid
hearing no sense restraint is
restraining your senses including your
own mind so when you have these you have
something challenging comes up uh you
need to restrain yourself from trying to
deal with it on that specific level and
not lose perspective that the problem is
it's the mind that gets loose that
escapes the enclosure and then starts
spinning and acting and and doing and
then I suffer thus if I refrain from if
I if I basically restrain my urge and
impulse to yeah jump with that mind and
go and try deal with seemingly what
caused me suffering but instead just
remain um watchful of that mind so it so
so so it's kept and
closed I'll stop
suffering but that's that's the
challenge in the beginning so what do I
do well that's what you do don't fall
into a trap of trying to deal with
things specifically thinking that's
where the problem was but actually
remain fully
guarding that mind from
escaping into uh into the the the the
projected kind of idea of where the
problem was yeah you want to tame it
that's your sole goal and everything
that comes your way oh he said this and
we have this issue or that issue or I
remember this and my trauma of that all
of that is just to tempt you to give in
and let that mind go Le dead wild untain
mind back into
Wilderness uh either uh intentionally
volitionally or kind of through through
through lapsing of perspective so all of
the issues are not really issues they're
just there to to distract you from what
the real issue is which is the
Wilderness of the
mind so if you have kept the precepts
and if you practice the sent strain that
will become more and more clear so
doesn't matter what comes your
way the the the more things come your
way the harder you turn towards that
mind remain remaining locked and
contained everything then basically with
the right perspective EV everything
becomes a
reminder of where the emphasis should be
which is contained
mind so event and eventually it
it like any animal trainer would know it
you say that you break its Spirit kind
of thing that meaning you break its
Wilderness break its Wilderness yeah so
it calms down you're not actually and
it's happier actually of course
absolutely absolutely you're not
breaking its Spirit like making it sad
or something sure you're breaking it its
evil spirit you can say that you're
breaking the spirit that causes harm to
itself and you so in other words as a
skilled training train trainer you would
have things and sounds and images and
memories coming up but your eyes remain
on the animal you're watching its
reactions you yourself are not directly
concerned with anything that your senses
are uh coming across including your own
mind so it's all around but you are
keeping the eyes on that contained mind
and see its reaction see if is it
flinching is it is it trying to react
and pick those signs and recognize that
there is still room for improvement or
no look it's completely calm and he just
looking back at me and it's paying no
attention to these things that
mind and then you know and that's
exactly the simile of the cows and the
shepherd when when he recognizes then he
can even relax he can go to sleep under
a tree he knows it will not go too far
it will not react or the similar of the
battle elephant where eventually when he
has been properly trained even when it's
in Taken amidst into the core of the
battle where he's being prodded with
Spears and Loud drums and screams and
stuff it doesn't Flinch it doesn't move
it does not try to sort of you know shy
away it's just there kind of uh
resilient to all of
that so then then the Mind becomes as
pliable so like uh you can you can tell
it to do whatever you wanted to do then
you have learned how to speak to it so
to speak you you won't be trying to just
stop it stop it but you know you know
that if you do this mind does that if
you do it like this the Mind does
something else so you have learned you
have found the ways of communicating
directly to it which is an indirect way
from where you are when you start
practicing when you start practicing
everything is in front direct uh
objective experience my mind intentions
wanting to do this not wanting to do
that but actually uh mind does not
respond to that first it needs to be
contained indirectly caught up then wait
until it comes down then through sense
restraint and so you get to learn its
signs and features like what does he
want to do when pleasure is present what
does he want to do when pain is present
what does it inclin to does he do I just
allow it to welcome it relish it think
about it more like yeah but see do and
you can catch yourself it's not going to
be perfect say pleasure comes and and
you have lapsed and you're sort of
proliferating and fantasizing and then
you catch yourself and again you have a
choice when you catch yourself it's like
I must stop Yes you must stop but also
you need to know why you're
stopping so it's like okay so I can
continue this I can continue allowing
and and fueling these thoughts further
myself but I should not forget that that
is the direct cause for the Mind still
being unamed so then when that untain mind
unamed so then when that untain mind
when me paid with theed mind Untamed
mind encounter something in the world of
a displeasing Kind well that mind will
probably turn against me turn against
itself it will cause trouble and I will
be the one feeling
pain that's like the most direct method
for mental training for like you can
practice concentration all you want
focusing all you want but all of that is
making you it's not making you any more
aware of your mind of that wild
animal but if you recognize that when
you catch yourself in these UNH
wholesome behaviors you you sort of uh remember
behaviors you you sort of uh remember
recollect the context of and the
connection between the two the
connection being this Behavior I can
handle it doesn't do anything to me but
it fuels the Wilderness of my own
mind so then as I already know on
account of my limited
experience that mind when he doesn't get
what he wants uh when he gets what he
doesn't want when it's separated from
the things he wants to be United with
when it's United with things he wants to
be separated from I'm the one suffering
on account of it
it so I have a choice to continue
following my desires to continue
ignoring my intentions and all of that
will maintain the Wilderness of that
mind which means all of that will keep
me paired with
suffering but if I don't then do these
things and keep containing the Mind keep
taming it through that containment and
not providing unsuitable food for it the
mind will stop
reacting in the ways that cause me
suffering so then I will be free from
suffering and once you confirm that for
yourself the inability to suffer because
the mind cannot
do those Wild Things anymore cannot
crave against the pain cannot crave
towards pleasure uh that's when you know
okay this is the the beginning of the
Right View because there is no second
Arrow following not cuz I'm hiding
behind the tree it's just because the
first Arrow struck and the animal my
mind mind is
unmoved and he struck again on another
occasion and he was still unmoved struck
again on another occasion and he was
Again unmoved by that time you know okay
he's not going to move so you start to
develop confidence in your own training
that has been successful because the
animal is not moving and then you
wouldn't even have to know as in the
beginning you might be still a bit
doubtful oh will it move will it not but
when it doesn't move number of times
even that doubt would just evaporate and
you will not be able to doubt what's
already there un moving and you
realize you realize that your mind
realized for
itself that's how you know that you know
you know that the Mind knows now you can
now you can you can open the gates
because because that's what the Su
described like arand he knows that he
knows it's not just he had a knowledge
of something he knows that he knows so
it's like a double two tier knowledge
and that's exactly what it is you know
that your mind now knows for itself
you've been training it and now you know
that that mind has seen for itself that
this is more
beneficial than what it used to do when
it was
wild and and as I said again just to
repeat basically that's the it all boils
down to if you keep the precepts like the
to if you keep the precepts like the
Buddha tells us how to communicate with
the mind right from the start it's like
how do I become Sana well by practicing
the gradual training which starts with
the PJ keep the
PJ keep the
precepts guard of the Guard the sense
those see the danger in the slightest
fault watchful Be watchful of your
intentions actions things you Delight in
and that's how you are speaking to your
mind already even if you don't know that even
already even if you don't know that even
if you still don't see the mind you
already started
communicating certain things certain
information you already started
communicating with that Mind by
developing gradual training and then the
time will come when you're going to C
catch on and you will recognize oh yeah
the mind is actually now becoming more
pliable because of everything I've been
doing before the aggregate of virtue
that I developed watchfulness of my
intentions all of that oh that's why now
I can see this mind not running away as
before before not acting as wild as
before and then you can carry on
speaking to it in the same manner but
now you know for yourself now you see
how what you're doing is directly
communicating certain uh intentions
certain meaning certain information to
that
mind and yeah that's like the
kind of has another layer that analogy
of the the language like we said you
it's like you speak English but your
mind speaks the sign language for
example so you speaking English and
waving your arms mind does not hear what
you're saying but it picks on you waving
arms and you know the whole energy your
sort of output of it and and you don't
even know what you're telling through it
all you might be calm down calm down
what you're actually saying it is
craving craving more craving
and and the mind reacts to
that and and basically you don't even
know that you are fueling it because you
don't know what communication sign the
Mind picks on stop it stop it stop it
stop you're communicating the opposite
of
what yeah exactly even the opposite
that's what like but but just stop I
just want this mind to stop I just want
this thinking to stop causing me
suffering but your whole intention
behind it the the the the the the the
sign language of that intention the
movements of that intention are telling
your mind just go wild with it that
craving you've been doing more well here
I'm adding more fuel for
it so until you learn first for
yourself where the emphasis should be so
it's and and that's see the the the
point there is that the emphasis for
everybody it's like oh what I want and
what I choose and what's right in front
of me so I want this I don't want that
so in this case I want mine to stop I
don't I'm telling it I'm wishing for it
but all that is irrelevant all of that
is just you uttering words that the mind
doesn't understand instead of you
wishing for the mind to become peaceful
and trying to really concentrate into
the peace and so
on keep the precepts guard the sense
doors moderating eating see the danger
in the slightest fault watch fullness of
your intentions from the moment you
awake till you go to sleep don't act out
of anything and awesome even if you
don't wish and don't speak to your mind
to calm down it will cuz that's the
language of calming it down